<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>A counterbane against earthly carefulnes In a sermon preached at Cranebrooke in Kent. 1617. By Mr. Paul Baine ...</title>
            <author>Baynes, Paul, d. 1617.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1618</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 58 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 17 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2013-12">2013-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A06004</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 1638</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S101575</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99837384</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99837384</idno>
            <idno type="VID">1703</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A06004)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 1703)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 912:08)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>A counterbane against earthly carefulnes In a sermon preached at Cranebrooke in Kent. 1617. By Mr. Paul Baine ...</title>
                  <author>Baynes, Paul, d. 1617.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[8], 25, [3] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed by H. L[ownes] for Nathanaell Newbery, and are to be solde at his shop vnder St. Peters church in Cornehill and in Popes-head Alley,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1618.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Printer's name from STC.</note>
                  <note>Cf. Folger catalogue, which gives signatures A-D⁴ E² .</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the Henry E. Huntington Library and Art Gallery.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Sermons, English --  17th century.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2012-11</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-12</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-01</date>
            <label>Claire Tolan</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-01</date>
            <label>Claire Tolan</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-02</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:1703:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:1703:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>
               <hi>A</hi> COVNTERBANE againſt EARTHLY CAREFVLNES.</p>
            <p>In a Sermon preached at Crane<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brooke in Kent. 1617.</p>
            <p>By M<hi rend="sup">r</hi>. <hi>Paul Baine</hi> ſomtimes Preacher of Gods <hi>Word at Saint Andrewes in</hi> Cambridge.</p>
            <q>
               <bibl>
                  <hi>1. Pet. 5.7.</hi>
               </bibl>
               <p>Cast all your care on him for hee careth for you.</p>
            </q>
            <p>LONDON</p>
            <p>Printed by <hi>H. L.</hi> for <hi>Nathanaell Newbery,</hi> and are to be ſolde at his Shop vnder S<hi rend="sup">t</hi>. <hi>Peters</hi> church in <hi>Cornehill</hi> and in <hi>Popes-head</hi> Alley. 1618.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="dedication">
            <pb facs="tcp:1703:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:1703:2"/>
            <head>To the Right worſhipfull S<hi rend="sup">r</hi> 
               <hi>Willi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>am Crauon,</hi> Knight, and one of the Alder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men <hi>of the Honourable City of London,</hi> Eternall Happineſſe.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">R</seg>Ight worſhipfull and worthy Sir, hauing receiued an aſſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red teſtimony of your fauour and loue, and not beeing able to render, nor your Worſh. ad-mitting the moſt vſual gratifications; I am in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forced, becauſe I would auoid Ingratitude (a vice moſt odious vnto God and man) to ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nifeſt vnto you my thankefull mind in this ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner, altogether out of my element; but that it hath pleaſed God to diſpoſe of it ſo fitly, that in the very <hi>Interim</hi> of your fauor this Sermon was broght vnto my hands, without a Patron, to bee publiſhed in the world. And ſeeing I
<pb facs="tcp:1703:3"/> conceiued it not conuenient ſo to ſend it forth incident to ſo much enmity in regard of its op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſition to the worlds affections, I preſumed to make bold with your worſhip, who had bin my patron to entreat your fauor alſo towards this orphane, that vnder your protection it may paſſe more ſafely &amp; freely into the hands and hearts of worldly men. And indeed it will be very neceſſary for them to carry this Anti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dote alwaies about them neare their harts: for ſo ſhall they eſcape that death which by earth<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly carefulnes is ready to ſeize vpon them. For the more the world is drowned in worldly luſts and cares, (as hardly was it euer ſo deep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly as now) the more requiſite is it that there ſhould be all meanes vſed to pull men vp out of this whirle-pit wherein they are diuing vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to their euerlaſting perdition: now what means can be more effectuall heereunto, than the ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plication and fit application of that which our bleſſed Sauiour himſelfe hath preſcribed to this purpoſe? euen to turne our mindes from ſeeking earthly things which periſh with the v<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing (&amp; for the getting and vſing whereof God will require a ſtrait account at our hands) vnto thoſe things which are ſpiritual and will endure
<pb facs="tcp:1703:3"/> with vs to our comfort for euer. And heerein did the reuerend and learned authour of this Sermon expreſſe himſelfe to be a wiſe ſteward, <hi>viz.</hi> by giuing a fit portion to worldly men in fit ſeaſon. For if it could once be fixed in mens mindes to loue Gods kingdome and his righ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teouſnes, ſo as to ſeeke it firſt of all, and to be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leeue that all neceſſary earthly things ſhould be added vnto them; then the deadly cares of the world would vaniſh away &amp; trouble them no more, at leaſt nothing ſo dangerouſly. But this is rather to bee wiſht than hop't for, in re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gard the world hath ſo deceiu'd men, that now nothing on earth is eſteemed good but that which is gaineful: nay goodneſſe it ſelfe findes little regard but for the gaining of earthly com-modity; ſo that moſt men ſet themſelues to catch at the ſhadow of good, in the meane time loſing the ſubſtance of it. Yet this eſſaie to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>couer men into their right mindes againe, and to reduce them into the true way of happineſs as it was moſt commendable in the holy prea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cher hereof: So I hope the publiſhing of it ſhall not bee vnacceptable vnto any. Howſoeuer, I humbly deſire your worſhips fauourable aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pect vnto it: &amp; if it ſhall pleaſe you (when you
<pb facs="tcp:1703:4"/> are free from greater affairs) to caſt an eie vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on it, I doubt not but you ſhall find ſomthing worthy your view and conſideration. But my ſlender commendations will but dim the ſplen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dour of this burning light: and therefore firm<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly hoping and humbly deſiring your worſhips pardon for my ouermuch preſumption, I com-mend you to the almighty pro<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ection of God the wiſe gouernor of euery thing in heauen &amp; earth; who makes all things worke-together for the beſt vnto thoſe that loue him.</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>Your Worſhips most humbly at command, <hi>N.N.</hi>
               </signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="sermon">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:1703:4"/>
            <head>A COVNTERBANE againſt EARTHLY CAREFVLNES.</head>
            <epigraph>
               <q>
                  <bibl>
                     <hi>Mat. 6.33.</hi>
                  </bibl>
                  <p>But ſeeke yee firſt the kingdome of God, and his righteouſnes; and all theſe things ſhall be added vnto you.</p>
               </q>
            </epigraph>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">W</seg>E will premiſe a few things concer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning the ſcope, coherence, parts and explication of this text, that we may come to the inſtructions which of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fer themſelues to be deduced from it. Our Sauiours ſcope is,
<note place="margin" type="RunSum">
                  <p>The ſcope of this ſcrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Contraria contrarijs op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>time curan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tur.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>The care of heauenly things a re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>medy a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt earth<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly carefulnes</p>
               </note> by a <hi>re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vulſion</hi> to heale an inordinateneſſe which was in his diſciples, in caring and ſeeking after the things of the world. Now this he doth by preſcri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bing a contrary practice, and making them a promiſe vpon the vſe of it: and therefore, wheras they were ſet vpon earthly things, he commendeth to them the care
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:1703:5"/> of heauenly; whereas their hearts were full of diſtruſt, earthly-mindednes, &amp; vnweanedneſſe from the things of this life, he wiſhes them to endeauour after true righ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teouſnes, which entring would free them more &amp; more from theſe defects.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin" type="RunSum">The cohe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence.</note> Touching the dependance of this vſe on the former, it may bee conceiued as a further reaſon, and ſo a newe ſtroake driuing the ſame naile, diſſwading their prepo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſterous ſeeking earthly things,
<note place="margin" type="RunSum">It is a new <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>eaſon.</note> which was the point the former reaſons did enforce: And then the argument co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cludeth thus: Theſe things, w<hi rend="sup">ch</hi> while you bend your ſelues after heauenly maters, will flowe in vpon you of their owne accord, thoſe you need not ſeeke ſo eagerly; but if you ſeek Gods kingdom, theſe things ſhall be caſt you in ouer &amp; aboue.
<note place="margin" type="RunSum">Or rather a new precept.</note> 
               <hi>Ergo &amp;c.</hi> Neuertheleſſe, becauſe of this particle (but) which maketh oppoſition, I doe not take it to be a farther reaſon, but a new precept pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcribing a contrary exerciſe, by which the diſeaſe now ſufficiently diſcouered might be healed in them.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin" type="RunSum">The parts.</note> The parts are two: 1. The duety required; 2. the rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon. In the duety there are three things. Firſt, The acte to bee donne, <hi>Seeke:</hi> 2. The manner, <hi>Seeke firſt.</hi> 3. the matter or obiect, <hi>Seeke firſt Gods kingdome and his righteouſnes.</hi> In the reaſo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> which is <hi>ab vtili,</hi> 3 things like<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe are obſerueable: 1. the things ſhould be giuen the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, <hi>and theſe things, viz.</hi> aboue-named, 2. the quantity of them, <hi>and all theſe things,</hi> 3. the manner of beſtowing them, in that laſt word, <hi>ſhall be added vnto you.</hi> Now for the more full explication of this Scripture,
<note place="margin" type="RunSum">The expli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cation. What ſee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king is.</note> wee muſt knowe, that ſeeking is an action of diligence and care, endeuouring to finde ſome good, which, after poſſeſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:1703:5"/> once had, is loſt of vs, or to obteine ſom good thing w<hi rend="sup">ch</hi> we yet neuer enioyed. See how Mary and Ioſeph ſought Ieſus when they miſſed him in their returne from Ieruſalem, <hi>Beholde,</hi> (ſaith his mother to him) <hi>thy father and I haue ſought thee with heauy harts, Luke</hi> 2.48. <hi>Seeke firſt,</hi> that is, in time, before other things, and with your principall ſtrength &amp; care. Gods kingdome is put ſo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>time for that ſtate of grace through w<hi rend="sup">ch</hi> God ruleth in the harts of his people, as, <hi>Rom.</hi> 14.17.
<note place="margin" type="RunSum">Gods king<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome is of grace,</note> 
               <hi>The kingdome of God is in righteouſnes, and peace, and ioie in the holy Ghoſt.</hi>
               <note place="margin" type="RunSum">or</note> But from this ſtanding in righteouſnes, peace, &amp;c. it is heere diſtinguiſhed, and ſeemeth therefore to be taken for that heauenly kingdome of glory;
<note place="margin" type="RunSum">of glory.</note> in which wee muſt conſider firſt, the place and glorious manſions, in which as euerlaſting tabernacles we look to dwell here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>after. For heauen is a place, yea, a bodily place,
<note place="margin" type="RunSum">whoſe place is bodily.</note> which ſhal properly receiue and meaſure our bodies glorified. If it be called a ſp<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>rituall place, it is to be vnderſtood re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpectiuely, as the body is cald ſpiritual, ſo far forth as ſpi<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>rituall is oppoſed to natural, not to corporal &amp; ſubſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiall. This heauen is not like theſe naturall and aſpec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>table heauens, which we now ſee, yet is a ſpace propor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tioned to ſuch bodies as are to be receiued and contei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned in it. Secondly,
<note place="margin" type="RunSum">Glory is 1. in the en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dowment of ſoule and body.</note> wee are to conſider the glorious e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtate which ſhall there be reuealed, which ſtandeth 1. in the glorious endowments of ſoule and body. For the glorious light of the ſoule ſhal make the body lightſom and glorious, as the candle doth the lanthorne in which it is carried. 2.
<note place="margin" type="RunSum">2. in our communion with God.</note> In our communion which we ſhall haue with our God himſelf, whom we ſhall ſee as he is, thogh we cannot throughly comprehend the infiniteneſſe of
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:1703:6"/> him.
<note place="margin" type="RunSum">which is the chiefe.</note> And this is the height of our happineſſe. For looke as a bride is nothing ſo happy in her bridall appa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rell and ornaments, as in her husband to whom ſhee is hand-faſt: ſo ſhall it bee with vs, our glory ſhall bee no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing to vs in compariſon of our God.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin" type="RunSum">Gods righ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teouſneſſe is that in Chriſt by faith appre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hended.</note> 
               <hi>Seek his righteouſnes:</hi> Gods righteouſnes is ſomtime put for that righteouſnes that is in Chriſt our great God and Sauiour, and is by faith laid holde of by vs. Thus it is vſually taken, <hi>Rom.</hi> 1.17. <hi>For therein is the righteouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes of God reuealed from faith to faith.</hi> And <hi>Rom.</hi> 10.3. <hi>For they being ignorant of Gods righteouſnes, and going about to eſtabliſh their owne righteouſnes, haue not ſubmitted them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelues to the righteouſnes of God:</hi> Sometime for that righ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teouſnes which God commandeth in his law being ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rituall,
<note place="margin" type="RunSum">Or that wrought in vs by the ſpirit.</note> and which God workes in vs by his ſpirit, when now through faith wee haue vnion and communion with Chriſt. Now the lawe of oppoſition doth lead vs to vnderſtand the righteouſnes which is wrought in vs. For as thoſe heauenly things next before vnfolded are moſt directly oppoſed to earthly: ſo to their diſtruſt in Gods promiſes, vnweanednes, earthly mindednes, the contrary graces inhaering in vs ſtand in moſt direct op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſition againſt them. Now the things which l<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>e are vniuerſally promiſed, are thoſe things which <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turally ſeeke,
<note place="margin" type="RunSum">Earthly co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forts promi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed.</note> or all thoſe things which God kno<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> we need, whether abſolutely, or in reſpect of dece<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> and conueniency, all things needful to our being or <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing. <hi>Shall be added vnto you:</hi> that is, ſhall bee giuen you as a vantage,
<note place="margin" type="RunSum">as a vantage.</note> ouer and aboue thoſe heauenly things af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter which you endeauoured. For the word is taken fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> thoſe additaments w<hi rend="sup">ch</hi> by ſurpluſage are caſt in to ſome
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:1703:6"/> full number. The ſumme is, as if he had ſaid,
<note place="margin" type="RunSum">The ſumme</note> I haue diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwaded you from inordinate purſuing theſe outward things; now I preſcribe you a contrary practice: Seek before all things, &amp; with your principall ſtrength, thoſe things aboue kept in the heauens for you; endeauour your ſelues to get you harts ſtabliſhed with true righte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſnes, ſuch as God commandeth in his ſpirituall law, and worketh by his ſpirit: do thus and you ſhall bee no looſers; For all things which are needfull for your be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing &amp; wel being ſhal as a vantage be caſt on you through the faithfulnes of your heauenly father who careth for you.</p>
            <p>Now wee come to the inſtructions.
<note place="margin" type="RunSum">Inſtructions</note> Firſt, wee will conſider of the duty required, <hi>Seek Gods kingdome, ſeek his righteouſnes:</hi> Secondly, the manner of perfourming, <hi>Seeke firſt:</hi> From the firſt obſerue here,
<note place="margin" type="RunSum">1. doctrine. Chriſtians ought to ſeeke heaue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>.</note> that true Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtians muſt here on earth ſet themſelues to ſeek heauen and heauenly glory: <hi>Seeke Gods kingdome.</hi> So Col. 3.1. <hi>If ye be riſen with Chriſt, ſeek the things that are aboue;</hi> and againe, <hi>Philip.</hi> 3.20. <hi>Our conuerſation is in heauen, from whence we looke alſo for the Sauiour, the Lord Ieſus, vvho ſhall change our vile body, &amp;c.</hi> Abraham, <hi>Heb.</hi> 11.9.10 is ſet before vs as an example of this thing, <hi>who did cou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t euen the land of promiſe a ſtrange country, looking for &amp; ſee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king after a city which hath a foundation,</hi>
               <note place="margin" type="RunSum">It is their place and country.</note> 
               <hi>whoſe builder and maker is God. For that kingdome aboue is their proper place and natiue country,</hi> 2. <hi>Cor.</hi> 5.2. <hi>and they are but ſtrangers on earth, Pſal.</hi> 119.19.
<note place="margin" type="RunSum">Th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>y haue <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>n inclinati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on toward it i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> born a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ew</note> An inclination &amp; affection ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore toward heauen is giuen to euery Chriſtian, when now he is once begotten and borne anew to God: Like as when any heauenly body is engendred heere belowe
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:1703:7"/> out of the proper place of it it hath begotte<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> w<hi rend="sup">th</hi> it an in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clination to riſe vp to that place to which it belongeth: as the fire,
<note place="margin" type="RunSum">A<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> fire to it's ſpi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="3 letters">
                     <desc>•••</desc>
                  </gap>e.</note> which here we kindle, and is engendred be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowe here on earth, it being no earthly but a heauenly body, hath from the firſt being an aptnes and inclinati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on carrying it toward the ſphere of fire w<hi rend="sup">ch</hi> is the pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per place of it: ſo from what time we by Gods calling are begotten heauenly creatures here on eatth, we haue produced in vs an inclinatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> which doth make vs moue toward heauen and heauenly glory, the proper place &amp; condition w<hi rend="sup">ch</hi> belongeth to vs. Would not an Engliſh man,
<note place="margin" type="RunSum">Or an exile to his coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>try.</note> (by any caſe exil'd) much long to ſmell the ſmoke of his natiue cou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>try? Thus, if we be heauenly creatures, we cannot but in deſire aſpire thither while we are here on earth as exiles and pilgrimes from our heauenly fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther.</p>
            <p>But before we come to the vſe of this poynt, we will more at large branch forth this duety of ſeeking Gods kingdome,
<note place="margin" type="RunSum">Gods king<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome is ſought.</note> by poynting forth the meanes and reſpects in regard whereof wee may performe this duety of ſee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king, here enioyned.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin" type="RunSum">1. by ſeeking diuine knowledge of it<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> chiefly from the miniſte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry of the word.</note> The firſt reſpect is, when wee ſeeke to get our ſelues informed in thoſe things which it becommeth vs to know and to doe about this kingdome. Now wee doe this, when we come forth to be inſtructed by the word of God which is the word of the kingdome. Looke as a man ſeeketh earthly things, when he goes out to the Crier to learne of them: and, look as clients ſeeke their earthly inheritances, when they go forth to aduiſe w<hi rend="sup">th</hi> their learned counſell; thus, when we go with diligence to the miniſters,
<note place="margin" type="RunSum">proc<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>nes.</note> who are <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> or <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, <hi>Ro.</hi> 10.14
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:1703:7"/> that is, <hi>Criers by office, who proclaime the bringing to light of this kingdome by Chriſt:</hi> and <hi>when wee waite at the poſts of Wiſdome her gate, Pro.</hi> 8.33. like as clients doe, atten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding on Gods miniſters, who are to know the lawes of this kingdome, that men may ſeeke them from their lips.</p>
            <p n="2">2.
<note place="margin" type="RunSum">2. By get<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting eui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence to ſhew for it, whi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>h are the promi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes thereof beleeued on</note> We may ſeek this inheritance of Gods kingdome in getting ſomething which we may ſhew for our right and title to it: Now, this we do by exerciſing our faith in ſome promiſes, by which God doth freely paſſe it vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to vs: as <hi>Feare not little flock it is your fathers will to giue you a kingdome, Luke</hi> 12.32. <hi>If we be ſonnes wee are alſo heires; euen heires of God, &amp; ioynt-heires with Chriſt, Rom.</hi> 8.17. <hi>God gaue his ſon, that whoſoeuer beleeueth in him, ſhould haue euerlaſting life; Iohn</hi> 3.16. <hi>We are begotten by the reſurrection of Ieſus Chriſt vnto a liuely hope, euen vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to an inheritance immortall, vndefiled, and which fades not away, reſerued in the heauens for vs, which are kept by the power of God through faith vnto ſaluation that is ready to be reuealed in the laſt time,</hi> 1. <hi>Peter</hi> 1, 3, 4, 5. Thus men ſeeke their earthly matters whilſt they gette good co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pies for that they holde. Now, the promiſes of GOD laid holde on are the onely deed and inſtrument which can be ſhewed for title vnto eternall life.</p>
            <p n="3">3.
<note place="margin" type="RunSum">3. By en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tring poſſeſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion of it in a ſanctified life.</note> We may ſeeke this kingdome in regard of getting our ſelues poſſeſſed of it: which wee do by this meanes, while we labour by a ſanctified courſe to drawe nearer it and enter it heere on earth. Men will not onely gette right vnto the things they ſeeke, but they will endea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uour to be poſſeſſed, to dig their turfe in that land they purchaſe. The more the Iſraelits did ſubdue the Cana<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>anites,
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:1703:8"/> the more they were poſſeſſed of Canaan.
<note place="margin" type="RunSum">Sanctificati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on is an en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trance into glory.</note> Thus the more we ouercome our ſinnes, growe in graces, the more we growe ſeized of our heauenly Canaan. <hi>Ioyne</hi> (ſaith <hi>Peter</hi> 2. <hi>ep.</hi> 1. <hi>cap.</hi> 5.6.7.) <hi>vertue with your faith, and with vertue knowledge, &amp; with knowledge temperance, and with temperance patience, and with patience godlineſſe, and with godlineſſe brotherly kindneſſe, and with brotherly kindneſſe loue:</hi> For as it after followeth, <hi>ver.</hi> 10.11. <hi>If theſe things be among you, ye ſhall neuer fall; For by theſe meanes an entring ſhall be miniſtred vnto you abundantly in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the euerlaſting kingdome of our Lord and Sauiour Ieſus Chriſt.</hi> The further that one did goe vp into the porch of the temple, the nearer he did come vnto the holy of holies; the further one goeth vp in the ſuburbs of a city, the neerer hee approcheth the citie it ſelfe: Thus it is herein the viſible church, our ſtate in ſanctificatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> hath it ſelfe to glory in the ſame proportion that our beeing in a porch, or body of a church, to our beeing in the quire; or our beeing in the ſuburbs to our entring the city it ſelfe.</p>
            <p n="4">
               <note place="margin" type="RunSum">4. By procu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring it aſſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red to vs.</note> 4. We may ſeeke it in regard of getting our title and poſſeſsion made ſure to our conſciences. Thus we ſeek earthly inheritances, not only to be ſeized of them, but by ſtrengthening our ſelues in them. Hence it is, that we will ſue out fines and writs, which may in a manner after a certaine time put an end to all claimes w<hi rend="sup">ch</hi> may bee made by any, ſome few perſons on iuſt ground ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cepted. So we muſt giue all diligence to get theſe things aſcertained vnto vs;
<note place="margin" type="RunSum">From the promiſe of Gods pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tection.</note> which wee doe chiefly, while wee faithfully lay hold on Gods promiſes, w<hi rend="sup">ch</hi> promiſe our protection: as, that hee is our God, who will keepe vs
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:1703:8"/> from euery euil work to his heauenly kingdome;
<note place="margin" type="RunSum">2. Tim. 4.18 The witnes of the ſpirit</note> while wee get the Spirit to witneſſe to our ſpirits this gift of perſeuerance which is beſtowed on vs; while we learne to dye by faith; Chriſt,
<note place="margin" type="RunSum">Faith in Ch<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>iſt pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>ruing and <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>aiſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ng vs, &amp; God kee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ping to by his power.</note> as the authour &amp; finiſher of our faith, and raiſer of vs vp at the laſt day: and the Father, who is ſtronger than all, keeping vs in his hand euen by his almighty power, as in a ſtrong tower vnto ſaluati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on. Wee can neuer be ſure enough of earthly things; we deſire to ſee the bird in the cage, and haue all things ſo ſettled as there may be no queſtion. How much ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther ſhould we not content our ſelues with vncertaine hopes of our heauenly inheritance, but trauaile to haue it ſettled on vs and throughly aſſured to our ſoules.</p>
            <p>Finally,
<note place="margin" type="RunSum">5. By praier for all help<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> vnto it.</note> wee ſeeke the kingdome of God in all theſe reſpects ioyntly by making petition to him. Euen as ſubiects by making requeſts get many things fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> their Soueraignes: ſo do we, who haue no way of getting a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny good thing, but by flying vnto his grace in Chriſt. Thus Chriſt taught vs to ſeeke. <hi>Lord let thy kingdome come. Mat.</hi> 6.10. Thus, <hi>The Spirit helps the faithfull with fighes and groanes that cannot be vttered. Rom.</hi> 8.26.</p>
            <p>The vſe of this is to rebuke moſt Chriſtians,
<note place="margin" type="RunSum">Vſe. The re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proofe of the worldly minded who dot<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> on earth.</note> who in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deed liue as Heathens. For, what doe they ſeek after, but ſuch things as Turkes and Pagans ſeeke after? <hi>Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny ſay, Who will ſhew vs any good? Pſal.</hi> 4.6. <hi>Many there are,</hi> ſaith <hi>Paul, Phil.</hi> 3.18.19. <hi>of whom I haue told you of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten, and now tell you weeping, who do minde earthly things:</hi> but the matter of Gods kingdo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> lies by a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> a refuſe thing quite forgotten. It is the wiſe merchant only,
<note place="margin" type="RunSum">Neglect <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ods king<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome. For want of true wiſdom</note> who <hi>ſee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>keth precious pearles, Mat.</hi> 13.45. Worldly men wanting that wiſdome from aboue are no more affected toward
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:1703:9"/> this heauenly inheritance, than thoſe who are born de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtitute of ciuill wiſdome are toward earthly. Theſe we ſee, not hauing ciuil vnderſtanding wherby to diſcerne the worth of their hopes, they neuer ſet their mindes vpon the faire poſſeſsions they might haue, but vaniſh away in trifles correſpondent to their weakenes: ſo do al natural men, who vnderſtand not the things of God; they are careleſſe of this kingdome of God, and glori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous inheritance, being wholly taken vp with a commo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> wealth fitting their kinde, the halfe-penny tranſitory things of this preſent life. And as the poore Iſraelites were ſcattered ouer al the land of Egypt to gather ſtub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble and picke ſtrawes, <hi>Exod.</hi> 5.12. ſo doe theſe range all the country, and are diſperſed all abroad to picke &amp; gather vp worldly things no more in compariſon than ſtubble and ſtrawes. Wherefore let vs not bee in the number of theſe fooles, worſe than any who are vſual<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly begged; let vs ſet our harts on this heauenly inheri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance;
<note place="margin" type="RunSum">We are to ſe<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ke out <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>e<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>u<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>nly in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>heri<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>nce. By <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ll good cou<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>s.</note> let vs ſeeke to be informed about theſe things; let vs get ſure conueiances; let vs by the conqueſt of all ſpiritual enemies enter this heauenly Canaan; let vs la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bour to get our conſciences aſcertained, that we ſhal be kept ſafe in this grace in which wee ſtand in the hope of glory. If wee haue right vnto and hope of earthly mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters,
<note place="margin" type="RunSum">V<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>l<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ſſe we wil<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> be more earn<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ſt for earthly things th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>n it.</note> we will not faile to ſeeke after them; yea, (though we be poore, and they that detaine them mighty,) wee will ſue <hi>in forma pauper is,</hi> but wee will recouer them; nay, if we haue loſt but trifles, if any ſilly beaſt be ſtrai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed from vs, we will aske and enquire after them: And is ther any thing more worth thy care &amp; pains in look<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing after, tha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> gods kingdom &amp; thy eternal ſaluatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>? can
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:1703:9"/> a man bee perſwaded that he hath great &amp; goodly poſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeſsions befallen him though in remote parts,
<note place="margin" type="RunSum">S<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>w <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ur v<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>b<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="5 letters">
                     <desc>•••••</desc>
                  </gap> conce<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="4 letters">
                     <desc>••••</desc>
                  </gap>g <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>t.</note> but his mind wil run much on the matter? his deſire will be to heare and ſpeake of it, to make a iourney to ſee it: Can wee then bee truely perſwaded, that an heauenly king<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome is giuen vs, but our thoughts will be vpon it? &amp; we ſhall deſire in Gods good time to ſee it. <hi>Where your treaſure is, there will your heart bee alſo, Mat.</hi> 6.21. Wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men haue in their wombes not onely liuing births, but ſometime alſo dead:
<note place="margin" type="RunSum">An<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="3 letters">
                     <desc>•••</desc>
                  </gap>i<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>e<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>e<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>es to be <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="3 letters">
                     <desc>•••</desc>
                  </gap>d Ch<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>i<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="4 letters">
                     <desc>••••</desc>
                  </gap>s.</note> now the former cannot liue alwaies pent in the womb, but it wil ſtriue for greater freedom; whereas the other haue no motion in them to come forth: thus it is with the church. She doth beare in her womb and trauaile of ſom liuing ſome dead births: the liuing, they will in their time ſtriue to come forth, cry<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing: <hi>Oh, vvho ſhall deliuer mee from this body of ſinne? Rom.</hi> 7.24. And, <hi>I deſire to be diſſolued, and to be vvith Christ, Phil</hi> 1.23. whereas dead Chriſtians they could be content to liue here alwaies, and ſing their <hi>Requiem</hi> heere on earth: if they may ſtill ſit in the warme ſunne, and haue wherewithall, they can eaſily forbeare all fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther happineſſe.</p>
            <p>Now, the ſecond matter we are to ſeek after,
<note place="margin" type="RunSum">2. Doctrine. Gods king<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not be ſought <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> Gods righteouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes.</note> is Gods righteouſnes: <hi>Seeke his righteouſneſſe.</hi> Where obſerue, That all true Chriſtians, yea, all who truely ſeeke the kingdome of GOD in the world to come, muſt ſeeke ſound righteouſneſſe in this preſent world. Theſe two God hath ioyned, and they may not bee ſeuered. For ſound righteouſnes is though not the cauſe of reigning,
<note place="margin" type="RunSum">It <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> to the k<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>g<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>d<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>
               </note> yet the way to the kingdome. Neither can any bee ſaid truly to ſeek that he may come hither or thither, when
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:1703:10"/> they doe not ſet a foote in the way which leadeth to the place they would come to. <hi>He that hath this hope,</hi> ſaith S. Iohn 1. <hi>Ioh.</hi> 3.3. <hi>in him, purgeth himſelf euen as God is pure.</hi> And ſo holy Dauid, <hi>Pſa.</hi> 17.15. <hi>As for mee I vvill behold thy face in righteouſnes.</hi> Hee knew no other way to come to the view of Gods bleſſed face, but by righteouſnes.</p>
            <p>Now, fully to open this, two things are to be conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dered: 1. what this righteouſnes is, or what it ſtandeth in: 2. the quality of it. This righteouſnes is ſimply in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>herent righteouſnes, and ſtandeth partly in putting off the corruption of nature; partly in getting the grace of Gods Spirit ſtrengthened and increaſed;
<note place="margin" type="RunSum">It ſtandeth 1. in putting</note> and laſt of all in the integrity &amp; perfection of ſpirituall actions. Theſe three dueties are required of the godly:
<note place="margin" type="RunSum">1. In putting off all ſin.</note> 1. The firſt we are exhorted vnto, 2. <hi>Cor.</hi> 7.1. <hi>Hauing therefore ſuch promiſes, beloued, let vs clenſe our ſelues from all filthineſſe of the fleſh and ſpirit, grovving vp vnto holineſſe in the feare of God.</hi> For like as light cannot enter further than darkeneſſe is chaſed, nor health returne in further de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gree than ſickeneſſe is remooued; ſo wee cannot for meaſure further growe in grace,
<note place="margin" type="RunSum">Without which is no place for grace. Chi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>fly natures cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ruption. And our actuall reig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning ſins. 2. In grace ſtrengthned &amp; increaſed.</note> than we finde corrup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion decreaſing in vs. And here we muſt labour chief<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly againſt that ſinne that dwelleth in vs, as the roote and fountaine of all ſinnes, to which by cuſtome, com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plexion, company, age or any other way we feele our ſelues moſt enclined.</p>
            <p>The ſecond thing we are exhorted vnto, 2. <hi>Pet. cap.</hi> 3. <hi>verſe</hi> 18. <hi>Grovve in grace and in the knovvledge of our Lord and Sauiour Ieſus Chriſt:</hi> wee muſt neuer ſtint our ſelues to a meaſure of grace, but bee euer comming on
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:1703:10"/> and growing forward.</p>
            <p>The laſt thing Dauid ſought,
<note place="margin" type="RunSum">3. In the ſoundnes of our action<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
               </note> whilſt he praied God to <hi>enlarge his heart, that hee might runne the way of his com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mandements, Pſal.</hi> 119.32. And this flowes from the former. For, looke as in the eye the more euery hurt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full humour is remoued, and the more the viſiue pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er is reſtored, the more perfitly and eaſily it ſeeth: ſo it is heere: the more ſinne is purged out, and grace in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>creaſed, with the more facility and perfection wee are occupied in euery good and ſpirituall word and worke.</p>
            <p>The quality is to be gatherd from that which here is added; <hi>his righteouſnes:</hi> that is, <hi>Gods,</hi>
               <note place="margin" type="RunSum">It is ſuper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>naturall and ſpirituall.</note> ſuch as God ſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pernaturally worketh in vs, ſuch as Gods ſpirituall law enioyneth; not ſuch as nature produceth, ſtanding in e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quity &amp; other morall parts,
<note place="margin" type="RunSum">Not morall</note> nor yet ſuch as hath a tinc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture of religion,
<note place="margin" type="RunSum">Not formal. Which is but counter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feit.</note> I meane a profeſsion of an outward forme of godlineſſe voide of power: for this is but a Phariſaicall righteouſnes, <hi>which ſhall not inherit the king<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome of God, Mat.</hi> 5.20. and is but like a beautifull pic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, which hath nothing in it but an externall appea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance. This thus opened lendeth light to conceiue the reaſon of this truth propounded. Euery thing that re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiueth being, nature doth giue it ſuch an inſtinct, that it ſeeketh to preſerue and bring on to perfection that beeing it hath receiued.
<note place="margin" type="RunSum">It is the be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing and life of a Chriſtia<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               </note> True Chriſtians hauing in their regeneration receiued a ſupernaturall being, euen the diuine nature or image which ſtandeth as in know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge and holineſſe, ſo in the righteouſnes here expreſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed,
<note place="margin" type="RunSum">Which he cannot but ſeeke.</note> they cannot but endeauour both to continue and take increaſe in this righteouſneſſe begunne in them. I ſay more, a Chriſtian cannot but ſeeke this righteouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:1703:11"/> more than heauen it ſelfe.
<note place="margin" type="RunSum">Y<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> m<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="3 letters">
                     <desc>•••</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap>.</note> For euery thing doth more ſeeke that which ſuſtaineth the beeing of it, and more declineth that which threatneth deſtruction to it, than it ſeeketh any thing which only conduceth to the more happy eſtate of it. Man more ſeeketh neceſſarie ſuſtenance for his life, more laboureth to expell ſome deadly diſeaſe, than in following wealth, honour and the reſt, which reſpect onely the well-being of it: thus heere it is; this righteouſnes is as it were the very being of a Chriſtian, heauenly glory is but his bliſſefull being, whence it is, that hee doth more ſeeke to get himſelfe healed of ſinne, the ſoules deadly ſickeneſſe; more ſeek to haue grace ſuſtained and increaſed; more ſeeke to haue integrity and ſoundneſſe in thoſe actions in which hee is exerciſed, than he ſeeketh heauen it ſelfe and that heauenly glory which is reſerued for him. It is the ſpeach of Anſelme well agreeing to this purpoſe. <hi>If I had ſinne ſet on this ſide of me, and on that ſide hell, ſo that neceſſarily I muſt bee plunged into one of them, I would ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther caſt my ſelf into hell than commit any ſin: And if I had on one hand righteouſnes offered vnto mee, and on the other Heauen, to take one without the other: I would much ſoo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner make choiſe of righteouſnes than heauen.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin" type="RunSum">
                  <p>The vſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>s <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap>. to ſhew their vanity who <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 span">
                        <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                     </gap> this <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 span">
                        <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                     </gap>.</p>
                  <p>N<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ho<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap> 
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="3 letters">
                        <desc>•••</desc>
                     </gap>ers o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> 
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>t.</p>
               </note> The vſe of of this is three-folde: Firſt, it letteth vs ſee the vanity of ſuch who thinke that they may ſeeke heauen well enough though they bee careleſſe of holi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, and neuer ſought to God to heale their euill harts, iudging themſelues and humbling themſelues vnder his hand; though they neuer knocked and cried for the increaſe of faith, knowledge &amp; repentance; nay, thogh they mocke at thoſe who follow righteouſnes, as men
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:1703:11"/> ouer-preciſe, holy, mad, forward,
<note place="margin" type="RunSum">
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> by Satan.</note> fondlings that know not what they would haue. The Diuell in outward things maketh men idolatrouſly leane to meanes; in ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritual things makes them preſume all without meanes:
<note place="margin" type="RunSum">Si<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="3 letters">
                     <desc>•••</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap> w<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>hout h<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap>. Eſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>. 5.<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>.</note> But <hi>without holineſs none ſhall ſee God, Heb.</hi> 12.14. And, <hi>the pure in hart onely ſhall beholde him, Mat.</hi> 5.8. Look as thoſe that were to ſtand before the Perſian Monarchs in Court, were to be clothed in royall apparell; and eſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pecially thoſe virgins w<hi rend="sup">ch</hi> were to bee brought as ſpou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes to them, they were firſt purified, perfumed,
<note place="margin">E<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>. 2.12.1<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
               </note> trained vp and prepared in ſundry kindes: ſo, all that ſhall bee married to God in Chriſt, or, that ſhall ſtand in the pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſence of his glory, muſt by this courſe bee made fit for ſuch a purpoſe.</p>
            <p>This alſo comforteth thoſe that ſeeke righteouſnes.
<note place="margin" type="RunSum">2. To com<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>fort the ſee<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>kers of it, who are true diſciples.</note> For it is an euidence, that they are the true diſciples of Chriſt, the beſt Chriſtians; that feeling their want and weakenes of grace, the preſence and ſtrength of ſinne in them, their bondage and lameneſſe in ſpirituall actions, doe ſeeke for grace for the crucifying of ſinne, and for their ſpirituall liberty.
<note place="margin" type="RunSum">And bleſſed</note> 
               <hi>Bleſſed are they that hunger and thirſt after righteouſnes, Mat.</hi> 5.6. Neuertheleſſe, as it is co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mendable not to reme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ber any thing paſt, ſo,
<note place="margin" type="RunSum">S<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>y growe on And take notice of Gods grac<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> toward the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> for thank<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ulnes <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>d comf<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>rt.</note> as to growe ſecure and idle, not ſtriuing to any further per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fection: ſo it is behoofefull to thinke how far God hath brought vs, ſo as to confirme our faith, and prouoke ourſelues to thankeſgiuing. There is a double hunger in nature: the one healthfull; the other no better than a very ſickeneſſe: for there is a diſeaſe called the hun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gry euill: when though a man bee full, yet hauing no ſenſe of his repletion, the ſtomacke doth as painefully
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:1703:12"/> and rauenouſly hunger,
<note place="margin" type="RunSum">Which good ſoules omit to their diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>comfort.</note> as if the man were affamiſhed. Thus it commeth to paſſe in Gods children; who, not conſidering nor getting ſenſe of that God hath done for them, are often as painefully hungry, as if they yet had receiued nothing at all which might ſtay their ſtomack. It is great pity that Gods children doe no more conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der this: It is ſurely a fault in them very preiudicial vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to their comfort, which they might reap by obſeruing Gods worke in themſelues, and grace toward them.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin" type="RunSum">3. To ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hort, to in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>creaſe in it begun in vs. Th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>t wee may differ from hypo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crites. Who wiſh for heauen, but neglect righteouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes.</note> Laſtly, let vs heere bee exhorted, that if euer wee did partake in the diuine nature, we do ſhew it by ſtriuing to growe in this righteouſnes which is begun in vs but imperfectly. This will argue vs to bee true diſciples. Such-like things as any ſeeketh, ſuch is the man. Bala<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>am may ſay, <hi>Oh, that my ſoule might die the death of the righteous, Numbers</hi> 23.10. But what doth the heart of a Dauid-like Chriſtian ſay? <hi>Oh, that my waies were ſo di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rected that I might keepe thy ſtatutes, Pſal.</hi> 119.5. For ſo Dauid beeing rauiſhed with a viewe of the good mans bleſſednes, doth preſently conceiue not this deſire, Oh, that I had this happineſſe; but rather this, Oh, that I could vſe the meanes to bring mee to it; <hi>Oh, that my waies were ſo directed, &amp;c.</hi> All after a ſort wiſh and ſeek heauen, but ſeeke not righteouſnes: But thou canſt not ſeeke the one without ſeeking the other; and finding this righteouſnes thou ſhalt alſo finde heauen, though thou doſt not expreſſely thinke vpon it.
<note place="margin" type="RunSum">Which will bring vs to heauen euen at vnawares. If we renew i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>.</note> Let a man go in this or that path, though he thinke not whither hee goeth, yet he ſhall finde himſelfe brought to that place to which the way leadeth. We muſt renew this ſpiri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuall beeing, as wee doe our naturall: Euen as in nature
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:1703:12"/> there is ſtill comming vpon vs a ſenſe of weakenes,
<note place="margin" type="RunSum">Wh<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="3 letters">
                     <desc>•••</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>o the ſenſe of inf<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>it<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="3 letters">
                     <desc>•••</desc>
                  </gap> do<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> t<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap>
               </note> and feeling of burdenſome ſuperfluities, that we might bee ſtirred ſtill to repaire and increaſe naturall ſtrength, &amp; expell that, which reteined would proue harmefull: ſo in the ſoule we haue weaknes euer and anon returning, that wee might neuer want a ſpurre to incite vs to ſeeke ſtill a freſh after the continuing and augmenting of righ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teouſnes in vs. Againe, if we haue ſome great bargaines we loue to finger ſome great earneſt: Now, thus it is,
<note place="margin" type="RunSum">And our better <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ſſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>r<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>nce draw vs.</note> that the very earneſt of heauen and heauenly glory pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſed, is this ſpirituall righteouſneſſe wrought in vs. Thus much for the dewty, now for the manner.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Seeke firſt.</hi> Obſerue heere,
<note place="margin" type="RunSum">3. Doctrine, Spir<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>uall things <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>re chiefly to be ſought. Iohn 6. Luke 13.24</note> that ſpirituall things muſt be ſought with our principall endeauours, we muſt nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther foreſlowe them, nor be negligent in following the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>. The Scripture biddes vs <hi>labour for the food that periſheth not:</hi> And, <hi>Striue</hi> (as for maiſtery) <hi>to enter; for many ſhal ſeeke to enter in, and not bee able.</hi> It forbideth ſlouth; <hi>Be not ſlouthfull but through faith and patience ſeeke to be par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>takers of the promiſes, Heb.</hi> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>.12. It commandeth vs all dilige<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce: 2. <hi>Pet.</hi> 1.5, 10. <hi>Giue all diligence.</hi>
               <note place="margin" type="RunSum">According a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> in price they pa<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>.</note> We ſeek things according to our eſtimate of them. And indeed euery thing is to be ſought more or leſs, as it is good more or leſſe; hence it is that things of no worth wee ſeek not at al, we let them lie vntaken vp: things of ſmall worth we ſe<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>k remiſſely; ſiluer &amp; gold, moſt carefully. Now, what is more precious than grace, or mo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>e excellent than heauenly glory? If therefore we count them before all things, let vs ſhew it by ſeeking them anſwereably.
<note place="margin" type="RunSum">And we meane to ſp<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="3 letters">
                     <desc>•••</desc>
                  </gap> Mat. 11.1<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>
               </note> Fer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uent ſeekers ſhall finde. <hi>The kingdome of heauen ſuffereth violence, and the violent doe take it.</hi> And ſlou<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>h in Gods
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:1703:13"/> workes is accurſed.
<note place="margin">Ier. 48.10. Mat. 25 26</note> 
               <hi>Curſed is hee that doeth the worke of God negligently;</hi> The ſlothfull and euill ſeruant entreth not into his Maiſters ioy.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin" type="RunSum">Vſes. 1. To blame ſuch a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> put off this care to the laſt.</note> Many may bee hence rebuked, who beginne at the wrong end, ſeeking the world for the preſent, and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeruing ſome purpoſes about theſe things in times to come.</p>
            <p>Againe, ſuch who though they doe not excuſe, and put off the matter for the preſent,
<note place="margin" type="RunSum">2. Such as poſt ouer re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligious due<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties ſlightly.</note> yet they poſt ouer moſt ſleightly all ſuch dueties, as concerne their ſoules health, thinking it enough if the work be done, though with neuer ſuch ouerture. Theſe commonly are wiſe in their own eyes,
<note place="margin">Pro. 26.16.</note> (like Salomons Sluggard, who <hi>thin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>keth himſelfe wiſer than ſeauen who returne an anſwere,</hi>) much condemning the forwardnes of others:
<note place="margin" type="RunSum">Condem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning others forwardnes.</note> What needeth all this adoe think they? God forbid no more ſhould be ſaued but thoſe few who are of this humour; There is a meaſure in euery thing; It is not our ſtriuing, but the good mercy of God that muſt ſaue vs. Thus, men are witty to pleade for ſinne, euen for that formall ſlouth that will ſlay them eternally. But let vs remem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber this,
<note place="margin" type="RunSum">Double dili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gence is to be vſed in heauenly things.</note> 
               <hi>Seek firſt,</hi> and awaken our ſelues, doubling our diligence this way. Nothing is more abſurd than to bring beetle and wedges to cleaue ſtrawes, doing trifles with ſuperfluous labour, and to bee careleſſe in matters of greateſt moment. Againe, wee ſee no earthly things of worth wil be atchieued without labor; they muſt be wooed, before they bee wedded; and ſhall wee thinke without ſeeking to atteine thoſe things which are the very vpſhot and harueſt of all our hopes? Thinke with thy ſelfe how men turne euery ſtone, and how many i<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rons
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:1703:13"/> they wil haue in the fire at once, that they may ga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther earthly treaſure. They will haue ſomething going in trade or ſtocke on their grounds,
<note place="margin" type="RunSum">Which we m<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>y <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> of good <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> for the world.</note> ſomthing by them for purchaſe, ſomething out at vſe, ſomething for bar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gaine and aduenture. If wee bee thus induſtrious in ga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thering treaſure vpon earth, which ruſt doth can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ker and the theefe robbe, how much more diligence ſhould wee vſe in getting heauenly treaſure, enduring ſubſtance? ſuch as grace, which ſhall neuer periſh, which ſhall not be left as earthly things are, but ſhall follow vs and dwell with vs for euer. Now followeth the rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>All things ſhould be giuen them.</hi>
               <note place="margin" type="RunSum">4. Doctrine The beſt way to thriue in the world is 1. to be rich in God. Who doth promiſe the godly 1. protection from hurt in his ſeruice.</note> Where obſerue that the next way for a man to thriue in his outward ſtate, is firſt to grow rich in his ſpirituall. <hi>Oh, that there were in you ſuch harts to keep my co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mandeme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ts alwaies that it might bee well with you and yours after you for euer</hi> (ſaieth the Lord) <hi>Deut.</hi> 5.29. For, firſt God doth vndertake to keep dammage from his, while they are occupied in his ſeruice. Looke <hi>Exodus</hi> 34.24. When all the males ſhould be gone to Ieruſalem, and none but weake wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men and children left at home, yet God doth vnder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>take that <hi>no enemy ſhould haue the hart to breake in on the.</hi> 2.
<note place="margin" type="RunSum">2. All good</note> God promiſeth to beſtowe on vs euery thing that is good: <hi>Pſ.</hi> 84.11. <hi>No good thing will he withhold fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> them that walk vprightly.</hi> 3.
<note place="margin" type="RunSum">3. A co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>table vſe of his bleſſings Iſa. 1.17.19.</note> God promiſeth to his a cheerfull vſe of all the good benefits vouchſafed them. <hi>Ceaſe to do euill, learne to do w<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ll, &amp;c: If yee conſent and obey, yee ſhall eat the good things of the land.</hi> Did not Ioſiah eate and drinke and proſper while <hi>while he executed iudgement &amp; iuſtice, Ier.</hi> 22.15. <hi>Godlineſs hath not onely the promiſes of
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:1703:14"/> this life, but of the life to come,</hi> 2. <hi>Tim.</hi> 4.8. He that giues the head,
<note place="margin" type="RunSum">Will not ſtand for ſmall mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters with them to whom hee hath giuen heauen. 1. Kin. 3.10 &amp;c. 10 13.</note> giues haire alſo: God giueth vs his kingdom and righteouſnes, which are principall, (which he euer doth when we ſeeke them diligently,) how ſhould hee not adde theſe inferiour things alſo which are but ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſary to the other? If hee did ſo like and recompenſe Salomons ſeeking of politicke wiſdome, which might ſerue him <hi>to goe in and out before his people,</hi> that hee gaue him it, and alſo peace and wealth which hee had not ſought; how much more ſhall he do this here promiſed to ſuch as ſeeke his kingdome and righteouſnes? Wee ſee earthly men, that if they haue a ſeruant, who is very diligent and faithfull in their buſineſſe,
<note place="margin" type="RunSum">Nor neglect a faithfull ſeruant.</note> though he hath not the skill to licke his fingers, and bee for himſelfe as many would; in ſuch a caſe will not a wiſe and equall Maſter the more beſtirre him to reward his ſeruice, by how much he diſcerneth him the leſſe to ſeeke himſelf? how much more then ſhall GOD doe for his ſeruants, whom he doth ſee to bee wholly bent to his buſineſſe? When the people followed Chriſt into the deſert,
<note place="margin">Mat. 14.19. &amp;<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>. &amp; 15.32. &amp;c.</note> God did rather by miracle feed them, than they ſhould want while they ſought his kingdome.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin" type="RunSum">Ob, concer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning the good mans croſſe<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> and the wickeds proſperity. Anſ. The croſſes of the godly are either chaſtiments of their <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="3 letters">
                     <desc>•••</desc>
                  </gap>lings: Or t<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ia<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>the<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="4 letters">
                     <desc>••••</desc>
                  </gap>ng to doub<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> pro<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="7 letters">
                     <desc>〈7 letters〉</desc>
                  </gap>, O<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap> w<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="3 letters">
                     <desc>•••</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>od and <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>w<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="3 letters">
                     <desc>•••</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> 2 C<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>. Cor. 2.9. Phil. 4.1<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>.</note> But it may be heere obiected, that the godlieſt haue the moſt croſſes and ſmalleſt meaſure of theſe earthly things; whereas the wicked are free from the croſſe, &amp; ſwimme with wealth.</p>
            <p>To the fi ſt I anſwere, that the godly man is often followed with croſſes, becauſe hee hath not followed righteouſneſſe, and liued godlily according as God re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quireth in his couenant. If he haue done this heere en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ioyned and yet haue croſſes, they are either ſuch as end
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:1703:14"/> after<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward in a doubled proſperity like Iobs, &amp; then this here promiſed is ſtil true or they are ſuch as dwel with him. In which caſe God doth recompenſe the want of out<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward things with himſelfe and contentation of minde. Thus Paul was <hi>in pouerty, in ieopardy, in hunger and thirſt, in cold and nakednes </hi> but hee reioyced in theſe infir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mities, and <hi>was enabled to doe euery thing through Christ ſtrengthening him.</hi> Now, this change is no robbery. And whereas it is ſaid that they haue not the greateſt meaſure of earthly things, it is co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>monly true: but their little is better than the abundance of the wicked.</p>
            <p>For firſt,
<note place="margin" type="RunSum">The ſub<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſt<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>nce of the godly <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>s 1. a token of Gods <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>e, &amp; from his owne hand. Gen. 3<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>.5.1<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> 2 An earneſt of their hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>u<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="3 letters">
                     <desc>•••</desc>
                  </gap>y inhe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritance.</note> it is giuen them from Gods hand as a token of his fauour. <hi>God</hi> (ſaith Iaakob to Eſau) <hi>of his grace hath giuen theſe children to thy ſeruant, and God hath had mercy on me, and therefore haue I all theſe things:</hi> Now an angell from the kings own hand is more eſteemed than much more other money which hath no ſuch reſpect.</p>
            <p n="2">2. It is an earneſt of Gods eternall fauour in beſtow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing on them the heauenly inheritance. Now, a little money that bindeth ſome great bargaine is better than much more that hath no ſuch relation.</p>
            <p n="3">3. It is freely beſtowed;
<note place="margin" type="RunSum">3. I<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> f<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>e<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="3 letters">
                     <desc>•••</desc>
                  </gap> giu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>.</note> they ſhall haue no reckoning to come in for it.</p>
            <p>Now,
<note place="margin" type="RunSum">The proſ <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity of <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>he wicked is but ſeeming b<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ing in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deed a curſe. As that which is <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>. mix<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>d of<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> with mu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>h diſco<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ce<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>.</note> the proſperity of the wicked is but in appea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance proſperity, being a pleaſant poiſon which killeth by caſting into a ſweet ſleep; or by mouing the perſon to laugh till hee fall downe dead by force of it. Euen as poyſon killeth ſome with intolerable gripings, others with very great delight: ſo doth Gods curſe ſinners.</p>
            <p>For the things they poſſeſſe, ſometime God doth mixe them with ſuch diſcontentmens that they are all
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:1703:15"/> as nothing; as is ſeene in Haman whom God did make the ſtiffe knee of Mordecai ſo to vexe and gall, that all he had did him no good <hi>Eſt.</hi> 5. And Ahab thogh a king, yet when he had the vineyard denied him grew ſo ſick of the ſullens, that hee could not ſo much as taſte ought of his kingly prouiſion, 3. <hi>King.</hi> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>1.4.</p>
            <p n="2">
               <note place="margin" type="RunSum">2. A ſn<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>re to them.</note> 2. If they haue the iocant vſe of things, yet it is no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing while God giueth them theſe things as ſnares to them, like as Saul gaue Michol to Dauid to bee a ſnare vnto him, 1. <hi>Sam.</hi> 17. Though it be not warrantable for a man in his policy <hi>demoliri honoribus,</hi> to ouerthrow men by aduancements, yet God (ſinne ſo requiring it) may do it moſt iuſtly.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin" type="RunSum">3. Not of Gods loue, but patience.</note> Againe, they haue theſe things but as traitours their allowance more or leſſe, from the clemency &amp; patience of the prince, rather than his fauour to them. Now, it is better with a poore ſubiect that workes for 12. pence a day with the kings loue &amp; protection, than with theſe haue they neuer ſo much.</p>
            <p n="4">
               <note place="margin" type="RunSum">4 Muſt be reckon'd for</note> 4. For theſe things are not giuen them freely, as by a father to his children, but rather giuen in as by an hoſt to his gueſts, for whom he keepeth a reckoning. The laſt diſh will marre their feaſt.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin" type="RunSum">The vſes, 1. to encou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>ge vs vnto godlineſſe.</note> The vſe is 1. to encourage vs in this work in making conſcience of it, knowing that it is not in vaine; but hath the promiſe euen of this preſent life. Haſt thou labou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red to ouercome ſinne, to growe in grace, to ſerue thy God more fruitfully and chearefully, and art thou ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uertheleſſe for the preſent in pouerty? Be not diſmaied, God oweth thee a good turne; he will recompence his tarriance, with vſe abundant. The ſunne ere while is
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:1703:15"/> long in getting forth, when yet the day prooues moſt faire and pleaſant.</p>
            <p n="2">2. Wee ſee the woefull ſtate of many,
<note place="margin" type="RunSum">2. To con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uince their errour who think<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> it the way to beg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gery.</note> who thinke this preciſe care of religion to bee the high way to the hoſpitall. If one ſtraine curteſie at one oath, if one will not borrow with the Sabbath for furthering his owne buſineſſe, if one will not keep lewd ſeruants when they are othwiſe gainefull, r, if one will not double with his tongue, vſe his wit to circumvent, if one will not humor thoſe from whom he may reape profit, if one will not dance to what the time pipeth, if one will not take any way to the wood, and lay about with ſixe fingers coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting al gain that may be gotten; Chriſtians now-adaies thinke ſuch a man may ſet downe his reſt for riſing.
<note place="margin" type="RunSum">Who are worſe than Sadduces.</note> O moſt vnchriſtian Chriſtians! worſe than the Sadduces; for that they did beleeue God ſo to proſper outwardly the keepers of his lawe, that hauing no beliefe of ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther life, (for they did think ſoules as bodies were mor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tall) yet they walked keeping the letter of the law moſt ſtrictly as their name doth intimate.</p>
            <p n="3">3.
<note place="margin" type="RunSum">3. To ſhew the cau<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>e why euen ſundry good husbands thriue not, That is t<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>eir neglect of religion. In the godly ſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>me ſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="3 letters">
                     <desc>•••</desc>
                  </gap> n<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>p<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>med of. Some infi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>y <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="4 letters">
                     <desc>••••</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cei<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="3 letters">
                     <desc>•••</desc>
                  </gap>.</note> Let vs hence take notice what doth keepe downe many in theſe earthly things, and clean ruinate others: What but lack of ſeeking heauenly things? There are ſome men of no lewd qualities, frugall enough, men a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble to make their market, yet nothing will go forward with them. And this is the iuſt iudgement of God, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe they neuer haue ſet their hearts to matter of reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion. Againe, many of Gods children goe backward in theſe things, becauſe they lie durtily without repenta<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce of ſome ſins w<hi rend="sup">ch</hi> God would haue them iudge in them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelues; or elſe they diſcerne not their infirmities, by rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:1703:16" rendition="simple:additions"/> whereof wealth would be hurtfull to them, and la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bour not to get them mortified. For God holdes down many,
<note place="margin" type="RunSum">Which w<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="4 letters">
                     <desc>••••</desc>
                  </gap>e <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap> pr<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="3 letters">
                     <desc>•••</desc>
                  </gap>y.</note> becauſe he doth ſee that if they ride on the fore horſe, and were aloft this way, it were for none to com neere them: Such is their pride that they would not knowe any; others to bee to contentiouſly giuen, that none ſhould liue quietly by them, but would bee euer puſhing and goring their brethren as buls do the wea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ker <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>artell with their hornes; others ſo voluptuous, that if they had wherewithall, they would runne riot into all intemperancy. Now a father will lay a knife out of the way from a child who is like to hurt himſelf w<hi rend="sup">th</hi> it.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin" type="RunSum">Hence is alſo the ru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> of many mens eſtates and how.</note> Farther, for the want of this God doth ruinate the e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtates of many by not keeping them from ſuch courſes of truſting, where what they truſt ſhall come home w<hi rend="sup">th</hi> loſſe; into courſes of ſuretiſhips, into ſuits of lawe and building, into dealing in things wherein they haue no iudgement, into the hands of vntruſty ſeruants (who are a backe-doore which will pull downe the greateſt houſes) that he may puniſh their not ſeruing him fruit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fully in the things they enioyed.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin" type="RunSum">4. To ſh<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>we<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>lth with<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>t go<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>lineſſe is no bl<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ſſing.</note> Laſtly, if thou haſt not beene a ſeeker of righteouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe and GODS kingdome, do not think the things thou haſt to be additaments beſtowed in Gods fauour, nor yet poſſeſsions making thee happy. They are but like that Manna which gathered beſides the Lords co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mandement did putrefie and come to nothing. So ſhall all theſe things,
<note place="margin" type="RunSum">But a curſe to greater <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>dgement.</note> they ſhall increaſe thy condemnation and make thee one day haue the heauier reckoning, if thou goeſt on in impenitency. Wherefore let me coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſell thee what to doe in this caſe. Didſt thou hold land
<pb facs="tcp:1703:16"/> on ſuch termes as would not maintaine thy title, but ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther expoſe thee to danger of accou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ting for all the time that thou hadſt helde them?
<note place="margin" type="RunSum">The onely way to ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cure thy ſelf is to turne Tenant to God.</note> Suppoſe thou mighteſt ſtrengthen thy ſelf in theſe by turning Tenant to the true Lord; wouldſt not thou readily put it in executio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>? Thus it is heere: All thou enioyeſt with careleſneſſe of Gods ſeruice &amp; ſeeking his righteouſnes, thou art ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iect to bee brought to a heauy reckoning for it, and to haue it taken from thee in Gods iuſt iudgement.
<note place="margin" type="RunSum">Tenant.</note> Turne therefore to him who is the ſupreme Lord, paie this rent which heere hee requires, ſeeke his kingdome and his righteouſnes, then thou ſhalt be happy in al thou poſſeſſeſt. To God the father, God the ſonne, and God the holy Ghoſt, be aſcribed (as it is due) all glory, honour, bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſednes, might, maieſty &amp; dominion, from this time forth and for euermore. Amen, Amen.</p>
            <closer>Soli Deo Gloria.</closer>
         </div>
      </body>
      <back>
         <div type="poem">
            <pb facs="tcp:1703:17"/>
            <head>To the worlds white Sonnes.</head>
            <lg>
               <l>
                  <hi>O</hi> Witleſſe mortalls! you all heedleſſe catch</l>
               <l>Appearing Shadowes; let the Substance go;</l>
               <l>At bables, bubbles, butterflies do ſnatch,</l>
               <l>But the true treaſure to ſeeke out forſlowe;</l>
               <l>Carke for your Carcaſe, it to clothe and feed,</l>
               <l>Your Soule leaue naked, and let pine for need.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>The nimble Fire ſtill vpward doth aſpire</l>
               <l>To its owne ſphere: and his deare natiue Home</l>
               <l>The wandring Exile euer doth deſire.</l>
               <l>The liuing Birth pent in its mothers Wombe</l>
               <l>Doth restleſſe ſtruggle for more liberty:</l>
               <l>But void of Motion the dead Mole dothly.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Were you from God with life diuine inſpir'd,</l>
               <l>Earth were too narrow to confine your Harts:</l>
               <l>Or were your Soules with loue ſpirituall fir'd,</l>
               <l>They would not dote on meere terreſtriall parts,</l>
               <l>But God would loue, and to enioy that Loue,</l>
               <l>Would vpward riſe and aime at things aboue.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Felt you your wants; moſt earneſt would your care</l>
               <l>Be for your Soule, your Bodie ſetting light.</l>
               <l>Knew you the world; its gariſh Shewes and rare</l>
               <l>You would deſpiſe, which but delude the ſight.</l>
               <l>Saw you Heauens bliſſe, baſe would the world appeare,</l>
               <l>But Heauen to win, no paines, no coſt too deare.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <pb facs="tcp:1703:17"/>
               <l>Which breathed in our foggie aire whilcome,</l>
               <l>But weary of thoſe ſtinkes it did diſcerne,</l>
               <l>To Heauens pure aire and cleareſt light is gone;</l>
               <l>Learne whither your chiefe labours to direct:</l>
               <l>Learne what ſucceſſe you may thereon expect.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Seeke Gods bleſt Kingdome, Seeke his Righteouſnes:</l>
               <l>All worldly comforts ſhall then follow you.</l>
               <l>Heauens ſhadovv is this earthly happineſſe:</l>
               <l>Who holdes the bodie hath the ſhadovv too.</l>
               <l>On thy Gods ſeruice do thou onely thinke,</l>
               <l>And hee'l prouide thee raiment, meat and drinke.</l>
            </lg>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>
